Shane Adam Young | Software Engineer

Software engineer with over 9 years of experience in finance and banking, with the ability to bridge both technical and professional interpersonal skills. A self starter that is motivated to find new ways to positively impact and evolve the world with the use of technology. My passion for lifelong learning drives me to continuously expand upon my skills and adapt to new challenges. With a strong business acumen, adaptable communication style and systematic problem-solving approach, I bring a unique and invaluable perspective to the tech industry.

Technical Skills

Languages - JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Python, SQL

Database - PostgreSQL, MongoDB | **Other** - REST APIs, JSON APIs, AWS, Heroku, GitHub, Git, Vite, Postman **Libraries and Frameworks** - ReactJS, ExpressJS, NodeJS, Django, Bootstrap

Professional Experience

Software Engineer | The Opportunity Project 2023 | Remote

08/2023 - Current

- Collaborate with a team of 15+ Software Engineers, Data Scientists, Data Analysts, UX/UI Designers, and UX Researchers
 on The Opportunity Project, led by the US Census Bureau, the US Department of Commerce, and the Consumer Financial
 Protection Bureau.
- Utilize federal data to build a web application that facilitates a more competitive credit card shopping experience for consumers and ensures that consumers have the ability to find the credit card that best meets their needs.
- Design a MERN stack application focused on financial education for first time credit card owners/users.

AVP - Portfolio Manager, Commercial Banking | U.S. Bank | Portland, OR

09/2021 - 05/2023

- Managed a dynamic \$65 million portfolio of commercial credit exposure, encompassing term loans, revolving lines of credit, and ACH transactions. Strategically allocated resources to optimize profitability and minimize risk.
- Conducted underwriting for new and existing clients via comprehensive written analyses that evaluates their financial statements and market trends.
- Utilized organization skills to manage multiple transactions in a time-sensitive manner, consistently exceeding expectations by completing transactions within 4-6 weeks.
- Leveraged Salesforce CRM to discover new revenue opportunities that also prioritizes customer success.

Portfolio Manager, Specialized Finance | U.S. Bank | Portland, OR

04/2018 - 09/2021

- Managed a portfolio of 55 customers, overseeing \$150 million in credit exposure across a wide range of industries, including healthcare, government, non-profit, and commercial & industrial sectors.
- Completed comprehensive credit underwriting requests for transactions exceeding \$1 million. Analyzed various credit information to assess credit worthiness and make informed decisions to approve or decline the request.
- Mitigated credit risk by analyzing operating performance, industry trends, and market dynamics. Tailored risk management strategies based on industry-specific risks.

Software Development Projects

Digital Payments App - Python, Django, PostgreSQL

09/2023

A feature-rich digital payments application, similar to Venmo, CashApp, and Zelle.

- Developed a comprehensive transaction handling system, allowing users to send and receive funds securely.
- Demonstrated competency in Django by creating dynamic views and managing complex data models for seamless application functionality.
- Designed and implemented core banking functionalities, including account management, KYC, and transaction processing.

Oregon Winery Review App - MongoDB, ExpressJS, NodeJS, ReactJS, JavaScript, CSS, BootStrap

08/2023

A MERN Stack web application for users to write their experience at wineries in the Willamette Valley region of Oregon.

- Implemented full CRUD functionality, enabling users to seamlessly create, read, update, and delete their reviews.
- Designed the application as a Single Page Application (SPA) using React, providing users with a seamless and responsive browsing experience.
- Utilized data seeding techniques to prepopulate the application's MongoDB database with a selection of wineries in Oregon, ensuring an engaging user experience from the outset.

Zero Based Budget App - MongoDB, ExpressJS, NodeJS, JavaScript, EJS, Bootstrap, CSS

07/2023

A budgeting application to simplify the process of tracking and managing personal finances.

- Built a full stack CRUD (create, read, update, delete) application in a one week sprint.
- Integrated Google OAuth authentication to streamline user access and enhance the application's security. Enabled users to log in using their Google credentials, ensuring a convenient and trustworthy sign-in process.
- Utilized Bootstrap to design a visually appealing and user-friendly interface.

EDUCATION

General Assembly, Bootcamp | Remote **Software Engineering / Computer Science**

05/2023 - 08/2023

University of Portland | Portland, OR B.B.A - Finance, Pamplin School of Business 08/2010 - 05/2014